<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss version='2.0' xmlns:atom='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'>
<channel>
<atom:link href='http://blog.j0ni.ca/' rel='self' type='application/rss+xml'/>
<generator>
clj-rss
</generator>
<title>
Diary of a Radiculopath
</title>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/
</link>
<description>

</description>
<lastBuildDate>
Fri, 26 Dec 2014 21:12:08 -0500
</lastBuildDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-05-10-fun-on-a-fixie.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-05-10-fun-on-a-fixie.html
</link>
<title>
Fun on a Fixie
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;Here are some rules I have discovered are the key to my buzz while I'm riding my fixed gear bicycle in the city. The city is Toronto, which is perfectly designed for riding such a bicyle, even if not brilliantly maintained for skinny hard tires and no suspension.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For context, I have only a front brake, clips on my pedals, and 2&quot; risers cut as narrow as I can get them and still have a reasonably accessible brake lever.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/photos/caine/7003907831/&quot; title=&quot;Untitled by Kwai Chang Caine, on Flickr&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6105/7003907831_c33f15f81b.jpg&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;Untitled&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They are written as goals. I probably achieve 100% maybe 1/10th of the time, but I'm getting better.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Start with a double espresso shot, preferably short.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Go fast.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Never unclip.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Never use the brake.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Never jump a red light.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;That's it. It makes for a completely engaged experience, the opposite of a commute on auto-pilot. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I recently learned to skid, which is making the no brake rule more achievable. I hope one day to ride without a brake, but I use it probably once every 5 or 6 rides at the moment, but when I do it's usually a last resort. Clearly I'm not quite ready to ditch it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm not obsessive about the road law - if I can ride up a one-way street the wrong way without getting caught, so long as it doesn't impede legal traffic, I will (I actually think that should be legal) for example. But the red light rule makes drivers hate us less, and combined with the never unclip rule makes for excellent track stand practice. I'm not totally on top of standing for long periods though, so I am not above propping up against a lamp-post at a light.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These simple rules have motivated me to get out on my bike most days for the last 18 months or more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Thu, 10 May 2012 00:00:00 -0400
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-02-24-eulogy.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-02-24-eulogy.html
</link>
<title>
Eulogy
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;Somewhat cliched, but it was written to be read at a funeral, the most indulgent of venues. Here it is for the record.&lt;h2&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re here to remember my mum, Hazel Irving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had a tough time putting down these words - of course I did, for all kinds of reasons - but one reason I had a tough time was because I kept realizing I’d forgotten entire chapters and subplots of her life.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You all know mum very well. Many of you know her far better than I do - I’ve only known her for half her life. There are almost 40 years I know about only through faded photos and legend.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s who she was as far as I can make out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She was an artist and a teacher. She was a musician and a performer. She was a great cook and an aspiring tractor driver. She was a cultural revolutionary; a shaper of cultural values. She was a hostess whose parties live on in infamy. She was a carer and a nurturer, not just as a mother but as a daughter, and later professionally in her role at the Park Lodge nursing home, I think because she couldn’t give it up. (I don’t recall her title, but you could call her “Quality of Life Manager” and you’d be close enough.) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She would not be fucked with (not that she was immune). She was bloody minded and not afraid to speak truth to power. She saw tact as a symptom of weak character.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She was not always right, but she knew her own mind, and was not afraid to share it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She was my mother, and in important ways, at important times, she was my mentor.&lt;h2&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, I was sent home from school with a violin, after scoring well on a pitch test at primary school. Later, she would tell the story that by this time she had pretty much given up on me as unremarkable and average. So this was like Christmas for her.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the years that followed, she drove my musical career hard. She would have me set up my music stand in the kitchen to practice. Quality control was a kind of audio/visual feedback system - I played, and no matter what she was doing, how busy or focussed she seemed to be, her visceral responses were my hard metrics. If my intonation was off, she would suck in her breath like I’d stabbed her with a fork or something.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I got it right, particularly after working hard at something for a stretch, her pleasure would fall upon me like mana from the gods. There was no richer reward.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Unconditional love is all well and good, but conditional approval is much better ego food.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week, as she lay struggling to form her thoughts, I played to her on a rented violin. Time and neglect have not been kind to my skills, but the time came at last when 10 minutes of “hard slog” paid off and a hard bit yielded to my will. Her approval sprang from nowhere (it wasn’t clear she could even hear me) and fell upon me again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I can tell you frankly and with no shame, at 43 years of age, I have found no reward since which I cherish so dearly as the approval of my mother when I play a few bars of music beautifully.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I lived without it for 25 years, so I know I can. But now it’s gone for good, and I will miss it.&lt;h2&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I called her as a cultural revolutionary. I don’t think she thought of herself that way, but she was part of a movement which was in my opinion revolutionary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She helped bring modern theatre to Leeds, and Leeds to the national theatre scene. She was central to the arts scene in Leeds for most of her adult life; as a performer, a campaigner for the first Leeds Playhouse at the University, and the current West Yorkshire Playhouse. Later, as a fund raiser and a volunteer - she created the Playhouse costume hire department and ran it voluntarily for many years. Even after her so-called “retirement”, helped raise money through her work with the Friends of the Playhouse - where she found many of you, her best friends of the last couple of decades.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She was a founding member of the Leeds Art Centre, and remained a vice president until she died.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When she finally stopped volunteering for the Playhouse, they gave her a lifetime season ticket.&lt;h2&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is true that life happens to us, sometimes in ways over which we have little or no control. But our lives belong to us. Terrible things may happen, leaving us depleted and damaged. But what we do with our experiences, and where we go next, these things are exclusively our property. Our choices belong to us and no other.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After she and dad split up, in some ways she never recovered. She had no interest in finding another partner, she really just wanted the original contract honoured. But she would not be defeated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She refused to be forced out of her home by the inevitable loss of income. As well as taking the job at Park Lodge, she turned our family home into a boarding house for international travellers, artists, actors, students, lecturers, possibly even a couple of eastern European spies. She didn’t just take them in, she made them her friends - sometimes not necessarily with their full co-operation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Later, when her body was devastated by two strokes so that she could no longer work, she remained defiant. She kept driving until we had the courage to make her stop (after a rather spectacular accident causing damage on both sides of a fairly wide road). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like the weird eastern European spies, she turned her stroke from enemy to friend. She became a stroke association activist, supporting and counselling new stroke victims. She would not be defeated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She refused to presume upon the favours of her friends, despite their frequent offers of help. And the offers were frequent indeed - if there was one thing she collected more of than her seemingly infinite owls, it was people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My mother was a strong and fiercely independent woman. And I choose my words carefully - she was fierce, and she was independent. She was a contradiction, born into a gender role our culture still can’t seem to shake, but unafraid to take on the intellect and wit of all adversaries, male and female. She taught us to be uncompromising, while living a life of compromise, but she would not be patronized and she would not be marginalized.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She spoke her mind, and she taught me to speak mine. She was and is a fine role model, and I miss her.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 24 Feb 2012 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-02-16-d.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-02-16-d.html
</link>
<title>
^D
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;Eveline Hazel Irving (née Hunter), born 1st January 1931, died shortly after 4am on 16th February 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rest in peace, sweet heart. Thank you for everything.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Thu, 16 Feb 2012 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-02-12-bow-shock.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-02-12-bow-shock.html
</link>
<title>
Bow shock
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;It's been just over two weeks since I last wrote. I'm having a hard time writing, because I've become more self-conscious. This is not my story, but it reads like my story. I mean, THIS clearly is my story, but it shouldn't be. That it is reflects my own self-absorption, or so it seems to me today. Also I'm getting less coherent by the day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don't want to lose track of what happened when though, so here's some bits and pieces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I did go back home to Toronto. I went and spent a night in London, hanging out with Haroon and then Karin, an old friend in Clapham. Haroon and I went to see Shaun of the Dead at the BFI with a Q&amp;A session (by Skype) with Edgar Wright and Simon Pegg afterward. While we were there, I managed to &lt;a href='http://www.flickr.com/photos/caine/6780773483/in/photostream'&gt;completely&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href='http://www.flickr.com/photos/caine/6780766795/in/photostream/'&gt;destroy&lt;/a&gt; my iPhone by grinding it to a pulp in the cinema seat mechanism. Joy. We went over to Covent Garden afterwards and bought a new one, since at this moment in my life I would rather deal with deferred debt than suddenly not having my phone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The week at home was traumatic and surreal. Everything there was pretty well normal. And after that sudden speedup at the end of the previous week, I was internally freaking out about whether I was going to make it back in time. All the while of course dealing with trying to work, and trying to extract (and deliver) full value from the week at home with my family.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the first few days of internal torture, a new kind of guilt-laden normality set in, and we had a really good birthday weekend for Lauren. Friday night, Lol and I went to see the Girl with the Dragon Tattoo (good but not as perfect as I'd hoped). Saturday we did the Eaton Centre (yay, NOT), the AGO, and wandered down to the Doc Martens store (largely squatted by Japanese hipsters) to buy her the most ridiculous boots we could find.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7144/6820380029&amp;#95;9fc26a833f&amp;#95;z.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stomping Boots&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sunday was a dark day for my soul, sitting and waiting to fly (2140 flight), watching Moon on Netflix, snuggling with Grace and Rachel on the sofa, feeling like I might not be back for some time. Having felt so wrong about being home at the start of the week, by the time I left I didn't want to go. Not that this isn't where I need to be. Just… well, it doesn't have to make sense.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So now I've been back a week, and things are moving quickly. Mum is dopey and increasingly confused. She can't hold her weight on her legs any more, so getting out of bed is out of the question really. She has the means to go potty without moving, but she doesn't &lt;i&gt;believe&lt;/i&gt; it, and when she finally does, she &lt;i&gt;hates&lt;/i&gt; the idea. And since she forgets, we have a little routine every few minutes where she tells us she's really going to have to go to the toilet, and we tell her about her magic pants. She laughs, comprehends, recoils, and on we go.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In any case, most of her physical sense of self (proprioception, sense of bladder or bowel state, hunger and thirst controls, etc.) is gone all to hell. Sometimes she's panicky and upset, and knows she's going &quot;round the bend&quot;, and &quot;losing it&quot;, and she doesn't want to die. We hold her hand, cuddle a bit, give her (or me) a lorazepam. Now she has a morphine prescription, taking another step toward the endgame. We try to talk about the old times and memories she does seem to have available because that settles her a bit and helps displace her thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was able to rent a violin and have been playing to her during the day. A couple of times she's starting singing along, or giving me congratulations when I work on a bit and finally get it right. Almost like old times. All I need now is a sharp intake of breath whenever my intonation sucks. That would get old fast of course, since my intonation sucks ALOT at the moment. I dig the gnarly gypsy violin I picked up though, it's all beat up and warm sounding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last two nights we've had night sitters coming in, which is a mixed bag. They are helpful, and we've gotten more sleep. But the reason we asked for them is that mum has been getting more agitated at night, sometimes a bit shouty and distressed, sometimes just talking lucidly about random things, then being asleep when you go to check. But whatever the reason, whenever you hear her, you have to go check. So sleep had become a fractured affair at best while I was gone, and when I got back it was clear that it wasn't sustainable. One thing about a week away, you notice changes where someone who has remained might have missed the increments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mum doesn't like being manipulated, and generally has a hard time being manhandled by strangers - the CAP teams who come to get her washed and dressed in the morning have felt her wrath on several occasions. Consequently, the night sitters are on very thin ice. The first one was lovely, and helpful, and mum seemed to like her. I stayed up with her just to be sure, and help with turning her (and learned a couple of useful things).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second one though, last night, mum absolutely hated. She had an agitated night and shouted at the nurse, insisting on going to the toilet (cue the aforementioned conversation loop) every few minutes, then dropping off. Tonight, she got so angry about it that she started screaming and hitting me. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm going to leave it there for now. I'm not sure how regularly I'll update any more. There's more to tell about today and tonight, but I have lost the ability to judge what it is and is not appropriate to share. I am tired and lost and confused, and a little bit drunk. Perhaps some clarity will return tomorrow. Or perhaps tomorrow will be more fucked up than today. That actually seems more likely.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Sun, 12 Feb 2012 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-27-clarifications.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-27-clarifications.html
</link>
<title>
Clarifications
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;The oncologist appointment is done, and I think that's it for our dealings with St. James', unless something happens and the crisis leads us to the emergency room. That's not the plan though, the plan is to be prepared and equipped, and to stay at home or at a push move mum out to St Gemma's Hospice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was a strange conversation, another of those where you aren't quite sure whether the doc is trying to assess mum's cognitive capacity, or is actually seeking information. Mum would give her usual glib and inaccurate answers to questions, glossing over or even just forgetting problems she's been having. We would sit to the side shaking our heads and quietly making corrections. Dr Turner explained to mum in detail, patiently waiting for her patterned replies to end. Eventually we got to the &quot;what happens next&quot; part, and I couldn't take any more of watching her getting more and more tense and annoyed with his continuing refusal to give her the reassurances she was asking for. I asked if we could let mum sit out the rest of the meeting. He put that to mum who of course was very happy to have Liz and me deal with it, and go out with the nurse for a cup of coffee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So the net of it all is this: The primary turns out to be melanoma. The site is not known and given a general lack of physical discomfort, irrelevant. The tumours in her brain will therefore not respond to radiotherapy. Wikipedia's 2.3 month median survival rate is pretty much &quot;on the money&quot;. Mum has a few weeks left most likely.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I asked him about my trip home, and whether I was making a mistake. He explained that several pre-terminal things might happen at any time, but setting those aside, the time to be away is now. If I don't do it now, I might not get home for weeks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So I will go home.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The best news is that the likely progress of this disease will be sleep and more sleep. As she loses function, she will sleep more, and the end will probably be just a failure to wake up. Seizure is possible but much worse to watch than to experience. Eventually, she may lose the ability to swallow. In that case, there is no alternative to oral administration of dexamethasone, so the medication will cease and her deterioration will progress much more rapidly from that point onward.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So we're back home, the hospital bed has been delivered and set up in the toy room on the ground floor. We're boosting the steroid dose back up to 16mg a day for the next few days, then dropping it back down again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mum went out for lunch with her friends, and Liz and I went over to her flat and started sorting through her desk and filing cabinets. There was lots of eye-rolling and exasperated expletives as we found all the dozens of &quot;important information about your account/policy/credit card&quot; leaflets carefully filed away. Years and years of Tesco's online shopping receipts. Cynically up-sold insurance policies (500k GBP buildings insurance for a 190k GBP flat? Fuck you Saga). Minutes from Friends of the Playhouse meetings going back seemingly indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think I'm going to scan and archive a lot of those mundane items. Not really sure why, but I can imagine meditating on them years from now in the middle of the night.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 27 Jan 2012 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-26-a-game-of-soldiers.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-26-a-game-of-soldiers.html
</link>
<title>
A Game of Soldiers
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;Being articulate, pushy, and in LS8 can open a lot of doors, and apparently get you to the top of the waiting list for an electric bed - it will be delivered tomorrow afternoon. But what the social services giveth, brain cancer squats on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mum took a bit of a dive today, around 5:15pm. She had been snoozing, and she woke up upset and confused with a headache and feeling nauseous. I gave her acetaminophen (yeah, that's how empowered I felt) and held her hand. I thought about what I should do for a while, and decided that since it's clear that there is nothing to be done, I shouldn't call anyone. Calling someone would just bring them round and create a crisis, and might conceivably end up in the emergency room. Fuck the emergency room. Fuck the ward. I want to know what's going on, but there's no good reason to investigate. It would involve scans and hours of waiting and well-meaning but brutally efficient healthcare professionals. And it would yield nothing of any value to us. Nothing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So I held her hand. After a while I felt guilty about taking a decision like that all on my own, so I called Liz. She was on her way home, so we talked after she got home. She agreed. Tim got home and he agreed too. It didn't help much that we were all of the same mind, but it helped a little.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She's definitely worse, more confused, she keeps her eyes closed, lacks strength and control, talks like a sleep talker, drags her foot instead of lifting it. But she doesn't seem any more unhappy, or to be hurting. This is the one thing which is missing, some way to cope with sudden discomfort. The best drugs we have here are lorazepam for anxiety. We should be getting some injectable meds for emergencies soon, which will render the question of calling someone out or getting her to a hospital entirely moot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I know I go on about this, but it is a serious head fuck to switch from a medical/curative mindset to a palliative/comfort mindset. In the new context, understanding what's causing the symptoms has no value. Nothing useful arises from it. All the available responses are the same, so why even ask the question? The question itself is upsetting, so it's better to &lt;i&gt;avoid&lt;/i&gt; the question. This is so hard to do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow is going to be a harrowing day. We're seeing the oncologist at 10am (first appointment - 3 weeks after diagnosis of brain mets, a disease with a median survival rate of 2.3 months, and that is a process accelerated by articulate pushiness and living in LS8 - all noted without comment for now). After talking turkey, we go home to a home visit from the GP. In some ways, mum being more distant and confused will make these meetings easier, because she will not be engaged in this discussion of the manner of her death. But the flip side is that her lack of fitness will mitigate against any treatments. I know it's not good to play &quot;what if&quot;, but seriously: What if radiotherapy was worth 3 extra months? And what if today's sudden downturn is the difference between viability for radiotherapy and not? Fuck that for a game of soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don't even know if going home this week is an option any more. I'll decide tomorrow night.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Thu, 26 Jan 2012 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-22-106-calories.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-22-106-calories.html
</link>
<title>
106 Calories
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;The lymph node is malignant. This doesn't come as a surprise, and it is good to have answered the question. Julia, a community care person from St Gemma's Hospice, was able to pull the results and also gave me the name of the oncologist to whom mum's case has been referred. I called the doctor's secretary and left a message. It was late Friday afternoon, so no response until Monday I expect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We haven't told mum yet. I have mixed feelings about holding it back, but that's literally all I know - there is evidence of malignancy. Everything else is conjecture based on previous conversations and assumptions I'm making. And I'm acutely aware reading back over this account that I've misinterpreted evidence previously. I'd hate to misrepresent anything, even if it's likely that mum wouldn't remember what I'd told her. So I'll wait for the conversation with the oncologist.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's a strangely blank feeling, knowing this. Like a door that I didn't think of as being open has closed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Liz and I talked a bit about how remote we've been feeling through all of this. There are moments of clarity, slaps in the face, during which we connect with it and feel guilt for our remoteness the rest of the time, but they pass. This isn't an unusual response to difficult emotions for me. At other times in my life it has been problematic, but this time I've been OK with it, because too quickly there will come a time when it isn't possible to background what's going on. Until that time comes, I am OK letting my analytical side manage the medical issues and letting the rest of it slide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The hardest times are visiting mum's flat to feed the cats. Not having been around day to day to see her, and seeing her life laid out around the place… imagining her there dealing with feeling like she was &quot;not all there&quot; (her words, a few times over the last few months), maybe over-medicating because she forgot that she took her meds already, spending most of her nights in her living room chair… That's when my remoteness fails me. That's why I don't go around there as much as I should, why I haven't been able to box up all her files and bring them over. It isn't the cat smell, although that's pretty bad.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until a couple of nights ago, I had convinced myself that the mental block I had preventing me from starting to gut her place and start working on fixing it up was the cats. Once we'd found a place for them I thought, we could start work. Then Tim mentioned in passing that even if we didn't start work on the flat with the cats gone, at least we could just close the place up and not deal with it at all for a while. And I felt a weight lift from me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I cancelled my return flight reservation to Toronto (I can re-book for $90 + tax any time up until January next year) and booked a new week-long return trip to Toronto for next weekend. I'll be back home for Lauren's 14th birthday.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Sun, 22 Jan 2012 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-19-good-times.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-19-good-times.html
</link>
<title>
Good times
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;It's been a week I guess, and I haven't written anything down. The details seem so incremental and banal, and it munges together in my mind. Also, I'm now working, around my sister's schedule, so time is short. But I don't want to drop this effort to keep track of things, because it's useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some things then:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Monday, we took mum down to St James' Bexley Wing, the new oncology building. It isn't much like a hospital, more like a posh mall with a touch of art gallery. There is a grand piano in the huge lobby near the obligatory Costa Coffee. One wonders when that gets broken out. Do people dance to quiet jazz? It seems wrong to have a live pianist in such an utterly non-smoking environment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was quite a long wait (partly because the appointment time we were given when we discharged mum last week was incorrect, although fortunately earlier than the real appointment), but the whole thing took about 20 minutes once we were in there. The doc looked around a bit using the ultrasound, found the lymph node, gave mum a local anaesthetic (the most painful part), and took the tissue sample. We watched the needle on the monitor all the way through.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite being told over and over by us and her friends how relatively innocuous the biopsy procedure would be, she was very anxious about it, and wound herself up into a bit of a panic as the appointment approached. Once in the waiting room, she was calmer but it was obvious she was working hard, and privately in hell. Afterwards, she was shocked that it was over, and very pleased that there wasn't much to it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think this is typical of one of the patterns she's developed, which is either caused by or maybe just exacerbated by her disease. She fixates on a misunderstanding which somehow becomes entrenched, and discards contradictory evidence. Sometimes it is something like this, grounded in fear of a real medical encounter. Sometimes it is pulled fully formed out of the air, or somewhere other than reality anyway. And because she doesn't retain the attempts to persuade her otherwise, it stays with her.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Something similar happened today. My old friend Fergus, who lost his mother to MS some years back, has been stressing the importance of seizing the opportunity to do things with mum while we still can - while she can still appreciate them. This is wise advice to be sure, and with that in mind we went out for lunch today to the Mansion, a place which was my local pub throughout my youth. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But mum really didn't want to go. She was lethargic and apprehensive, didn't think she could manage stairs, was still unhappy when we addressed that concern by offering to use her wheelchair and carry her up and down the stairs (which worked great, and didn't involve putting Liz's back at risk, so there). This is the same as the resistance to being upstairs in a bedroom, where no matter how much you explain that actually there are more people closer to her up there than downstairs so she will actually be &lt;i&gt;less&lt;/i&gt; isolated up there, she won't let that fact undermine her right to feel isolated if that's what she's decided. It is the same pattern as her seeming inability to internalize the description of the biopsy process that came from medics, friends and from us.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's easy to put this down to her disease, but she has &lt;i&gt;always&lt;/i&gt; been like this to some degree. Anyone who knows her will be familiar with her ability to completely reinvent memories, and even fully erase events that everyone else remembers. All in all, that this is not a new pattern makes it especially frustrating to deal with, because at one time anger and frustration seemed like a rational response, whereas now, at a time when her cognitive process is degrading, anger is really not at all appropriate. But you can't change an emotional response overnight.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course lunch turned out to be a good time, and she was very happy and proud to have made it out. The idea of all those people around that she had found distasteful enough to call out as a reason not to go became a cherished part of the warm fuzzy she seemed to be experiencing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7170/6720122283&amp;#95;5319425d3f&amp;#95;z&amp;#95;d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Good times&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Later, apparently, she proudly explained to visiting friends how she had walked around under her own power. I guess she forgot about the wheelchair too. No matter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Things are definitely worse than they were at the beginning of the week. Liz and I have talked about it and we agree, there is more forgetfulness, confusion, and something else I hadn't seen but Liz recognized from when she was admitted to hospital: she is keeping her eyes closed quite a lot, while awake and talking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow I am calling the GP to see if the biopsy results are in, and find out which oncology area we need to talk to at St James', so I can follow up and get a specialist assigned, and an appointment. I will mention this change and see if we can increase the dexamethasone dose again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This has rambled a bit - I think that will be the way things are for a while now I have less time to myself. I will bookmark here some thoughts to write about soon:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;I had a good conversation with Shahzeena, Haroon's partner, who is an oncologist. Useful information was imparted.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;I had a good conversation with dad over dinner. Emotional burdens were slapped on the table and compared.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Some thought has been given to my return to Canada, because I think I will be needed here for some time and I would like to go back for Lauren's birthday (14 was an important age for me, I would like to be there when her 14 starts). So for the first time in 12 years I will shortly be purchasing a return ticket from the UK to North America.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also, the ground here is wet ALL THE TIME.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Thu, 19 Jan 2012 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-13-transitions.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-13-transitions.html
</link>
<title>
Transitions
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;I'm having a tough time keeping track of everything. So many conversations, so many phone calls. And sometimes the things I've been saying over and over to different people and writing down here start repeating on me, coming back to me as if I heard them from someone else.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I touched on The Return yesterday. As we prepared to leave the hospital we learned a valuable lesson that's worth passing on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you are talking to doctors, you are dealing with people who live in an idealized version of the world. It's important that they are allowed to continue inhabiting this perfect vacuum, because otherwise they could not achieve the depth and breadth of detailed knowledge needed to support the key contribution they make to the medical process. Imagine attempting to fully comprehend the medical history and new clinical data of a human being, assess progress and make a recommendation for next steps, 25 times in the space of just over 3 hours.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But it is a medical &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt;, and although it hinges on the doctors, and without a hinge a door is just a broken wall, the rest of the door is much bigger and heavier, and that's what you have to put your weight behind to get it to open. It stands to reason that given that cognitive load (and I'm not talking about my door metaphor), there is absolutely no benefit to be derived from loading them up with the process data too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So when the doctor told us there was no medical reason for mum to remain in the hospital, she was, strictly speaking, correct. But a broader interpretation reveals that her analysis falls a little short of the truth. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;More specifically, while on the ward, post-discharge planning is handled by very competent senior nurses. Once discharged, those nurses are no longer involved in the planning process. Moreover, when a person is referred to social services and other community agencies as an inpatient, the case is treated quite differently and with greater priority than if they are referred as an outpatient.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mandy, the senior nurse who was overseeing mum's case on the ward, sat us down and explained this to us yesterday afternoon as we were psyching ourselves up to take mum home. I know that we would have gone ahead with discharging mum anyway, but it would be good to have had it spelled out earlier. Although Mandy tried to get the referral through to social services (for example) before we actually left the building, the fact that we were home by the time they saw it was enough to have it reclassified.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As it turned out, I spent quite a lot of time on the phone today, and made a lot of progress. We had a doctor's visit, got a referral to Macmillan Nursing, and made an appointment to have a home visit from the district nurse tomorrow to talk about regular care visits and potentially useful equipment. I don't know what kind of equipment that might be. A hydraulic bed or a powered reclining chair would certainly come in handy. We'll see. We have an &quot;emergency&quot; assessment from social services early next week, who are now treating this as a community referral rather than a hospital referral (or whatever the qualification that inpatient status confers is called). But I think we're doing OK without them co-ordinating, at least in the short term.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 13 Jan 2012 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-13-ancestral-home.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-13-ancestral-home.html
</link>
<title>
Ancestral Home
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;Just a short one tonight, I need to be up early to make some calls.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mum's home, or at least back at my sister's house (previously our family home). It is going to be a lot harder for us than we had imagined, but it is already better for her. I am concerned about how disjointed the next steps may be - referrals have been made, but we are in free fall until the actors have been identified, particularly the oncologist (yet to be assigned) and the case manager (a social worker, yet to be assigned). This is the price we will pay for discharging mum before all this was set up, because if she had stayed put, a very capable head nurse would have been sorting it all out. I hope we haven't made a dreadful mistake. I know mum is better off here, but I worry that we might have jeopardized the process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow we start haranguing people until all these dots have been joined up.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 13 Jan 2012 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-13-alice-is-wise.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-13-alice-is-wise.html
</link>
<title>
Alice is wise
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;My kids made cards for me to bring for mum. They're all wonderful, and capture each of their personalities beautifully. Alice is the most empathic person I've ever met, so I thought this was worth reproducing. It's the note inside the card she made.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt; To: Grandma Hazel&lt;br/&gt; &gt; From: ALICE/one of your grandchildren :D&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; &gt; I've really missed you in the 2 years that I've been back in Toronto.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; &gt; I really with I could be in Britain for Christmas and New Years but sadly we are running low on money and we cannot afford for all 5 of us to go, but on the brighter side: At least dad is coming (he's missed you a lot too).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; &gt; Dad is probably either reading this card with you or is watching you read it, Dad is a very dedicated son and father he loves you and he loves us, speaking of loving tell dad that we miss him and we love him, tell Liz, Tim, Louis and Noah that we hope they are well and once again I really miss you and hope you are better.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; &gt; - Alice &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 13 Jan 2012 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-12-wednesdays-child.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-12-wednesdays-child.html
</link>
<title>
Wednesday's child
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;I forgot to buy a toothbrush, and my electric one ran out of juice half-way through. It is testament to my pathological behaviour patterns that I have never in my life before heard an electric toothbrush run out of power.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today was the toughest day so far. Not because of any particular piece of news - we had the results from the body scan back, and a recommendation from oncology, but nothing definitive. It's really about the gradual transition to reality that's going on. We've been in a state of crisis, and now we're moving toward banality. On the way, there are incremental information updates, and a process of acceptance of the truth by mum, and many many bureaucratic obstacles and aids. There are expanding puddles of cat piss and shrivelling property values. There are bank accounts and some unknown number of forgotten investments. Mouldy fridges and buckled doors. Cryptic garbage schedules and pension credit savings credits.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scan highlighted only one interesting item, an enlarged lymph node in her groin. This is apparently not a prime suspect for metastasis to the brain. Prime suspects include breast cancer and melanoma. It's possible that the lymph node is doing something fairly normal and is not cancerous, but oncology recommends a biopsy, which has been booked for Monday. I'll come back to that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the doc mentioned melanoma, I remembered that many years ago mum had a melanoma removed from her leg. The doc was all over this, and noted that it may well be significant. She said she would pass on the information to oncology, and see if they still wanted a lymph node biopsy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But this is all incremental to this narrative, this surreal tale that's spewing out across our lives. The thing here is that it was the first time I've been with mum while she's had the situation spelled out to her. We've been generally pussyfooting around the details when we talk to her, using &quot;diplomatic&quot; language which will make sense to her only if she's already on the same wavelength, somehow trying to play to her state of mind but really playing to our own need to avoid the hard conversations. Today, we sat and listened and talked, and clarified so mum fully grasped the meaning of the words being used. While she struggled to find a natural reaction, my mind seemed to speed up and slide around the place, as if I was trying to correct for a slippery road, always overcompensating slightly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There's something about this, beyond just an urge to avoid difficult things. Like a child losing some piece of innocence, or just a parent finding out that it was lost long ago and having to accept that the delusion was on his part, not his daughter's - his own need to infantilize his child, blown apart by the realization that the child moved on to the next level, without clearing it with ground control.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm wandering, I know. But this has been a tough day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the most important things which was communicated today, and which we discussed later, giving me some confidence that mum has retained this information at least for now, is the notion that our focus now is palliative care, not a cure. There is no coming back from this, but there are people who will help us plan for the best possible death. I'm confident that mum knows this today, even if she won't know it tomorrow. By the time I left, she wasn't freaking out about it. That's blowing my mind. Maybe because I'm not ready to have her be better at this than I am.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another important revelation is that there is no medical reason for her to continue to be in hospital. Since her nights there are so desolate and horrible, and the prospect of another night alone has been plaguing her and causing her to fall apart as the end of visiting time approaches each evening, I think the very least we can do is get her out of there. So tomorrow, all being well, she is coming home to Liz's house. Clearly this can't be an open ended situation, so we will engage the palliative care team at the hospital tomorrow and get the ball rolling for a move to a care facility of some kind, tbd.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm finally beginning to grasp the scale of the work ahead of us, and it's quite frightening. We are going to need to find something on the order of 25k GBP per year to pay for care (I have no idea for how long). We're going to have to take apart her cat sanctuary of a flat and rebuild it, to either rent it out or sell it. We're going to have to dispose of furniture and carpets, and go through her stuff to find all her assets and income. And I'm running out of rope at work. Next week I have to start working again, I really do. I will need to write a project plan, down to the hours and the minutes, I think.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last of all, we need to decide whether to go through with the biopsy. We have to decide if we care about the results, and this is a new way of thinking which is difficult to accept. If there is a primary cancer in her lymph node, is that knowledge worth the discomfort and the atmosphere of medical progress the procedure will generate? If it turns out to be treatable, do we even want to be confronted with the decision about whether to treat it? Chemo and radiation are a horrible prospect, and will not bring about a cure of any kind. Why even go there?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One possible answer is that there are many kinds of brain cancer, and we don't currently have any information about the kind living in mum's head. Knowing more about its origin may help us understand its likely progress. This is valuable knowledge, to be sure. We have a few days to check our thinking, to make sure this is a rational decision.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's a strange way to have to start thinking. How do we judge that we're being too rash, trading off too much life expectancy in the hope of short term comfort? What kind of fucked up calculus can we use on this?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Forgive my incoherence. I guess I'm just incoherent at the moment. I was born on a Wednesday, as it happens.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Thu, 12 Jan 2012 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-11-awake.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-11-awake.html
</link>
<title>
Awake
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;United dropped off my bag today, so I finally got to brush my teeth. But of course I'd forgotten about the power diff, and unlike anything worth anything these days, my electric toothbrush charger can't step down the current, so I need to get a new toothbrush tomorrow. Oh well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today was a very mixed bag. Mum was better than yesterday, continuing a positive trend, and we had a lovely time sitting in the Costa Coffee franchise on the ground floor of St. James' Gledhow Wing (it doesn't smell like a hospital, earning it a huge thumbs up from me). I showed her photos from Rachel's flickr, we talked about things that had been going on when the pictures had been taken.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She even remembered that she'd been for her follow-up full body CT scan in the morning. What she didn't remember though, and what I found out from the head nurse person shortly before I left for the afternoon, was that the consultant doctor had been round earlier and talked to her in some detail about her disease, and about what she might do after she's discharged.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So it seems that the positive progress we've been seeing is due to the effects of the high dose of steroids she's currently taking. What this reveals (and I am unclear about why, but we will find out more) is that her symptoms are being caused by the cancer and not the bleed as we had hoped. This is bad news also because the steroid dosage is not sustainable indefinitely. When and how it is reduced is a medical decision which won't be taken until a more complete picture of her prognosis is available.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scan results will be in probably tonight, and the consultant will see them tomorrow. After that, all the medical reports and data will go to the oncology department, where it will be reviewed and a recommendation will be made. Tomorrow we may know more about the primary cancer, but Thursday is when we expect to start working on a plan for treatment and/or post-discharge care.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It looks like she won't be going home again, since her returning cogence is something of a mirage. She won't be capable of looking after herself, and will likely need 24/7 supervision for the rest of her life. It's hard to resist speculating about how long she has, and how that will go, but we're trying to avoid it anyway, until at least Thursday when the recommendations and analyses will be in front of us.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've been around someone who died of brain cancer before. It was very intense and difficult. I was much younger then, and hadn't seen as much, but it had enough of an effect that when I heard this news I immediately started harboring a secret hope that the primary cancer gets her first. I realize how blank and brutal that probably seems, but numb is where I'm living right now. Her generally good spirits are a surreal backdrop to all of this, and a gift from medical science to all of us. But it does make it easy to avoid the harshness of what lies beneath.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've been distracting myself a bit this evening with a little work email, and by skimming local bike shop websites and posting on the Leeds Fixed Gear FB group, looking for a ride I can pick up for the duration. I need to get out on two wheels, not having a bike here is making me feel fat and stuck. I know there's a big box store hybrid in the basement I can use, but that isn't what I need. I fear I might be about to throw my credit card a bone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So strange. Talking to Liz this evening, we compared notes on how we're talking ourselves distant from this, turning the words over and over, practicing them on our friends and mum's friends, so that they're an abstraction layer shielding us from what they represent. Is that good or bad? We don't know, but it seems wrong somehow, but thoroughly British.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Wed, 11 Jan 2012 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-10-home-again.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-10-home-again.html
</link>
<title>
Home again
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;Well, I made it here intact, although my luggage isn't here yet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has been a long day. I flew from Toronto to Washington Dulles after a slightly disturbing wait on the plane still at the gate while some dudes in reflective jackets tried switching the plane off and on again a few times all the while on the phone, presumably to tech support. Eventually the plane started working again, and we left. No aircon, but plenty of enthusiasm. It might have been cooler without the enthusiasm though, so fuck enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Made my connection at Dulles, where there were lots and lots of humans, all of them apparently pissed in one way or another. Didn't stick around and ask questions though. The plane to London was newish and fast, but no power, USB or otherwise. So I slept most of the way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;United didn't manage to get my bag onto my flight, despite having an almost 3 hour connection even given the inital delay. Oh well, they're only subhuman. But I packed my blood pressure meds in there, and my tooth brush, and my less stinky clothes, so I'm living without for now. They assure me my bag will arrive in the morning at my sister's house. I have no confidence at all.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Met up with Haroon in London and hung out with him until my train left at 12:35pm. He took me to drink coffee, eat pastries and buy mifi for my stay here. Now my phone and laptop are plumbed into my personal area network, and no more shall roaming data charges plague me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Haroon is a good friend, I am lucky to know him. He is sweet and sincere, and cares for those he likes and respects. A man with a big heart and a flexible schedule. In this way he is a Renaissance man, and a member of my tribe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Got to Leeds and met Liz at the station. We went straight to the hospital to see mum. Mum was in better shape than Liz was expecting, but the situation is the same and we have no new information. Here is what we do know.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mum had been complaining of growing befuddlement, troubled vision and more recently a vicious headache. On Christmas Day, Liz brought her to the hospital worrying about a possible new stroke (she had two strokes 15 years or so ago, I don't remember exactly how long, and never recovered full mobility or control of her right side subsequently). She had her meds changed, was looked over, felt better, and was discharged after a handful of days. Late last week she was in bad shape again, so Liz took her back to the emergency room at St. James' here in Leeds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This time she had a CT scan of her head, which revealed a 5cm bleed at the back of her brain. It also revealed a number of tumours distributed throughout her brain. The working hypothesis is that these are secondary cancers. Work to find the primary, should it exist, is incomplete. A further CT scan is planned for &quot;ASAP&quot;, but not yet scheduled. She will see a consultant physician tomorrow morning, and we hope to have more information in the afternoon. We have been told that the brain cancer is not operable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is basically the extent of the actual knowledge we have. She is being treated with steroids of some kind for the bleed, in the hope that this is not active, and may be reabsorbed. Only one CT scan has been done so far though, so we have no temporal data and therefore no definitive information about its progress, positive or negative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We've discussed this (and many other aspects of the situation), and have concluded (without professional advice) that the best possible case is this: that the confusion, befuddlement, troubled vision and headaches are the result of the bleed, and this is fixable; that the brain cancer is not aggressive and may be survivable for some longish period of time without devastation (our neighbour's father has lived with brain cancer for more than 4 years to our certain knowledge, probably longer, and is now dying of unrelated cardiac problems); that the primary either does not exist or is otherwise not aggressive, dormant, or treatable. These are extremely large &quot;ifs&quot;, and we have no viable way of quantifying the relevant probabilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most conceivable scenarios at this point are unpleasant and chronically traumatic. The situation is complicated by the fact that the befuddlement and confusion means that mum is not retaining information which has been given to her. Liz had decided early to keep the information about the cancer from her for the time being, at least until we had a more complete picture. A wandering consultant inadvertently shared the analysis, but mum had no recollection of it and still doesn't. This raises an ethical dilemma. Should a decision need to be made about treatment, things may become a lot more complex.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We've talked about it, and given her improving cogence (at least in the last couple of days) we will probably need to have that conversation, if the question arises. However, if she doesn't retain the memory of the conversation for very long afterward, we could find ourselves in the terrible predicament of having to make a choice between repeatedly giving her bad news and forcing upon her a decision no-one should ever have to take even once, or keeping information from her which no-one would doubt she has a right to know. This is going to take judgement, conviction and stamina on our part, and will I think damage us all.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And all the while there she is, frightened and alone at night, dreading being left in that place with people she doesn't know, confused, incoherent and unable to sleep. It doesn't take much thinking about that to bring me to the edge of my own sanity, so I can only begin to grasp what it must be doing to her.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally I'm ready to sleep. Here at last, I'm sitting at an unfamiliar dresser in a terribly familiar room, my own bedroom with it's cack-handed dormer windows which don't fit properly. I don't know how long I'll be here, but it feels like the best place for me to be.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Tue, 10 Jan 2012 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-07-passing-the-time.html
</guid>
<link>
http://blog.j0ni.ca/blog/posts/2012-01-07-passing-the-time.html
</link>
<title>
Passing the time
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;When I was 17 years old, my Nan died. She was very old (97) and in many ways her death was welcome - she'd been suffering from Alzheimers disease for several years, probably longer. Her death affected me in strange ways, mostly because she'd lived with us for my whole life to that point. As she fell into infirmity, my mother had more or less sacrificed her own life to take care of her, or so it seemed to me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My mum asked me to play my violin at the funeral. In my youth I was an accomplished violinist, and this was at the height of my musical career. After I left school a year or so later, I began a gradual and accelerating decline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But let's not dwell on that. Mum wanted me to play at her mother's funeral, and as far as I was concerned there was no-one else whose thoughts on the subject mattered at all. Of course I would play.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the eve of the funeral, my then girlfriend, Anne Marie, called and ended our 1+ year relationship - my first serious relationship. I was devastated. I went out with my good friend Andrew to the pub and drank away the crazy incomprehensible pile of wrong.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I played the last movement of Bach's Sonata for solo violin in A minor. I killed it (so to speak). My violin wept for us all and our short, pitiful existences. It was perhaps the darkest moment of my life to date, mourning a death, confronting my own rejection and inevitable loneliness, and all in the grip of a callous pulsating hangover. If you know the piece, you'll understand how perfect it was.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I found out that my mum is most likely dying. We don't know a lot yet, but what we do know is very bad. Tonight, a lot of memories have been bubbling up into my thoughts. I had forgotten about that performance I gave way back when, but it somehow captures in a single memory the challenge that's before me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don't mean to understate the challenge that's before my sister, and oh god, my poor frightened mum. But I can't be inside their heads.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I fly home to Leeds.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Sat, 07 Jan 2012 00:00:00 -0500
</pubDate>
<author>
J Irving
</author>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
